Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Miscellany, 1912-1951, undated (Box 8-9)
  - Address presented to Nikolay Medtner upon his return to Russia, 1927 (Box-folder 8/4)
    Includes the original copy with signatures and a typed translation.
  - Humorous scroll, July 11, 1936, A humorous paper scroll signed by several Russian individuals (London, 1936) encouraging Medtner to "apply himself with all diligence and perseverence to the learning of the barbarous Tongue of the hospitable Tribe we live amongst ...". (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Medtner Society publications, 1947-1949, Includes "His Master's Voice" announcement of the founding of the Society, programs of issued recordings (volumes 1-3), published reviews of the Society's recordings and other publicity. (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Musaget' catalogues, 1912-1913, Two catalogues. (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Royal Academy of Music. Diploma, June 28, 1928, The diploma was given to Medtner on the occasion of his election as an honorary member of the Royal Academy of Music. (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Plaster cast of Medtner's hands, ca. November 1951, Collection files paperwork describes this as a posthumous plaster cast of Medtner's hands. (Box 9)
  - Bronze bust of Medtner executed by Czech sculptor, Karen Vogel, undated, Consult Reference staff for assistance in examining this item. (Box:  Consult Ref. Staff)
- Books, 1826-1948 (Box 10)
  Eleven items, including two volumes of Pushkin's poems, single volumes of Lermontov and Tiutchev, all with Medtner's marginalia and musical sketches, as well as Medtner's personal copy of Muza i moda (Paris: Navarre, 1935) with autograph emendations, and Ėmiliĭ Karlovich Metner's Modernizm i muzyka (Moskva: Musaget', 1912).
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Drinker, Henry Sandwith. English texts for the songs of Nicholas Medtner. n.p., 1946., see ML31 .M43g no. 5 (Case) (Box 10)
  - Gebhard, Friedrich Albert. Dramatische Spiele. Queblinburg and Leipzig: G. Basse, 1826., see ML31 .M43g no. 7 (Case) (Box 10)
  - Holt, Richard. Medtner and his music: a tribute to a great Russian composer. London: Rimington, Van Wyck Ltd., 1948, see ML31 .M43g no. 6 (Case) (Box 10)
  - IAkovlev, Vasiliĭ. [Nikolaĭ̆ Karlovich Metner]. Moscow: [Musik Sektion, Staats verlag], 1927., Contains notes and other marginalia.; see ML31 .M43g no. 3 (Case) (Box 10)
  - Lermontov, Mikhail IUrʹevich. Lirika. n.p., 1921., Book of poems by Lermontov including Medtner's marginalia and musical sketches (page 9).; see ML31 .M43g no. 2 (Case) (Box 10)
  - Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich. Muza i moda. Paris: Navarre, 1935., see ML31 .M43g no. 4 (Box 10)
  - Metner, Ėmiliĭ Karlovich. Modernizm i muzyka. Moskva: Musageť, 1912., see ML31 .M43g no. 8 (Case) (Box 10)
  - Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich. [Unidentified collection of poems]. n.p., 1896., Inscribed to N. Medtner by Alexander Borisovich Goldenweiser, noted Russian piano pedagogue. (Box 10)
  - Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich. [Unidentified collection of poems], volume 2. n.p., 1921., This volume was used by Medtner when composing his songs based on Pushkin's texts.; Contains Medtner's musical sketches, marginalia.; see ML31 .M43g (Box 10)
  - Tiutchev, F. I. (Fedor Ivanovich). Stikhotvorenīi︠a︡. [Moskva: n.p., 1899., Volume of poems by Tiutchev used by Medtner when composing his songs based on Tiutchev's texts.; Contains Medtner's musical sketches, marginalia.; see ML31 .M43g no. 1 (Case) (Box 10)
  - Urania: Tiutchevskiĭ al'manakh, 1803-1928. Leningrad: Priboĭ, 1928., Marginalia found on page 269, which contains an article ("Tiutchev v muzyke" by Sergei Durylin) mentioning Medtner. (Box 10)
- Music, 1896-circa 1940 (Box 11)
  Three holograph scores and two printed music items. The holographs include: an undated score titled Romance, the first fair copy with composer's emendations for the Russian round dance, op. 58, for two pianos, and the Prelude, piano, E♭ minor, dated 1896. Printed music includes a printed score of Formes en l'air by Arthur Lourié (Paris: A. Gutheil, 1923), inscribed by Rachmaninoff, and a bound compilation by Kiselev of musical settings (by various Russian composers) to Pushkin's texts.
  Arranged alphabetically by composer/compiler's last name.
  - Kiselev, V. A. (Vasiliĭ Aleksandrovich), comp. Pushkin v romansakh i pesniakh ego sovremennikov. Moskva: Muzyka, 1936., Score, 224 p., 30 cm.; Songs with piano.; Musical settings of Pushkin's poems.; see ML31 .M43e no. 1 (Case) (Box 11)
  - Lourié, Arthur. Formes en l'air. Paris: A. Gutheil, 1923., Score, 9 p., 34 cm.; The title page contains a written dedication to N.K. Medtner in memory of the composer, initialed by Sergei Rachmaninoff.; see ML31 .M43e no. 2 (Case) (Box 11)
  - Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich. Prelude, piano, E♭ minor., Holograph manuscript score, in ink, 2 p., 35 cm.; Manuscript is dated 1896.; see ML31 .M43a no.1 (Case) (Box 11)
  - Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich. Romance., Holograph manuscript score, in ink, 1 p., 35 cm.; Melody with words.; Manuscript is undated.; see ML31 .M43a no. 2 (Case) (Box 11)
  - Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich. Russkiĭ khorovod = Russian round dance, op. 58, no. 1, for two pianos., Holograph manuscript score, in ink, 27 p., 34 cm.; Manuscript is undated but believed to be circa 1940.; see ML31 .M43a no. 3 (Case) (Box 11)
Alternate Forms of Names
(Alternate spellings for names in parentheses)
Conus, Leon (Konius, L'ev)
Conus, Olga (Konius, Ol'ga)
Conus, Sergei (Konius, Sergei)
Conus, Tatiana (Konius, Tatiana)
Dobuzhinsky, Mstislav (Dobuzhinskiĭ, Mstislav)
Kedroff, Nikolai (Kedrov, Nikolai)
Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich (Medtner, Nikolai Karlovich)
Paĭchadze, Gavril Gregorevich (Paitchadze, Gavriil Gregorevich )
Rachmaninoff, Natalie (Rachmaninoff, Nataliia)
Sabaniev, Alyota (Sabanev, Alëta)
Satina, Sofiia Aleksandrovna (Satin, Sophie)
Wolkonsky, Irina Rachmaninoff (Volkonskaia, Irina Rachmaninoff)